<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<cluster cid="IsraelPalestineConflict" lang="English">

<document did="israel1" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/fischer35/English">

<s sid="1">The End of the Two-State Solution?</s>

<s sid="2">2009-01-23</s>

<s sid="3" annotators="A B C">BERLIN – Since its establishment in 1948, Israel has fought seven wars against its neighbors, including the recent war in Gaza.</s>

<s sid="4">If you add the Palestinians’ first and second Intifada in the occupied territories, the total rises to nine.</s>

<s sid="5" annotators="B">From a military perspective, Israel eventually won all of these wars – or at least didn’t lose them.</s>

<s sid="6">But neither have these wars changed much for Israel in strategic terms.</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="A B C">Indeed, the core conflict between Israel and the Palestinians has remained almost unchanged throughout the past 60 years.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="A B C D">The United Nations’ Partition Plan of 1947, which split the former British Mandate of Palestine between both peoples, was not and still is not accepted until this day.</s>

<s sid="9">Sometimes one side rejects it; sometimes the other.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="B">This is why, to this day, people on both sides are dying.</s>

<s sid="11" annotators="A">Of course, Israel made a “cold peace” with Egypt and Jordan, and also established diplomatic relations with a few other Arab countries, but nothing has really changed at the core of the conflict, despite the Oslo peace process of the 1990’s and other treaties and agreements with the Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="12" annotators="A B">The central question for both sides remains unanswered: where does Israel end and Palestine start?</s>

<s sid="13" annotators="A C">Without a territorial compromise between Israel and the Palestinians, the conflict will go on endlessly, for it is viewed as existential by both sides.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="D">All those involved know that, in the end, only the borders of June 1967 – including Jerusalem and a negotiated, smaller territorial exchange – can be acceptable to both sides, however painful.</s>

<s sid="15">Everything else is evil wishful thinking for which more innocents will continue losing their lives.</s>

<s sid="16" annotators="B C">But, while it is abundantly clear that Israel will not vanish, and that the Palestinians will not wave the white flag, the conditions for a two-state solution are deteriorating.</s>

<s sid="17">It took more than four decades for the PLO to recognize Israel.</s>

<s sid="18">But, with Hamas’s victory over Fatah, the Palestinians have gone back to square one, to the rejection of 1948.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="C">Hamas rejects any peace with Israel, and is at best prepared to agree to a temporary truce.</s>

<s sid="20">Moreover, as part of the Muslim Brotherhood it also pursues an Islamist agenda, supported by Syria and Iran.</s>

<s sid="21">On the Israeli side, approximately 200,000 settlers on the West Bank and further development of the settlements weigh heavier than all noble words about two states.</s>

<s sid="22" annotators="C D">Given the facts on the ground created by Israel, there are justified doubts about whether a two-state solution is feasible at all.</s>

<s sid="23">The war in Gaza will harden this negative trend.</s>

<s sid="24">For one thing can already be said with almost complete certainty: the political casualties on the Palestinian side will include President Mahmoud Abbas and Fatah.</s>

<s sid="25">Their loss of legitimacy will not be reparable.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="C">Whatever becomes of Hamas in military terms following the recent fighting in Gaza, politically it has finally taken over the PLO’s role as the legitimate representative of the Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="27" annotators="A">This means that the West’s policy of isolating Hamas in order to weaken it, which has been pursued since Hamas’s victory in a free and fair election in 2006, has failed.</s>

<s sid="28">When the weapons remain silent and the dead in Gaza are buried, the question of a political solution will re-emerge.</s>

<s sid="29">An initial truce, by means of international mediation, can lead to a monitored long-term truce and reconstruction in Gaza.</s>

<s sid="30">But what then?</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="A C D">Both Israel and the West will no longer be able to postpone the question of how to deal with Hamas, because Abbas and Fatah are now too weak and discredited to negotiate a peace settlement.</s>

<s sid="32">And there is no easy answer, because Hamas will gain status through negotiations while maintaining its position to destroy Israel.</s>

<s sid="33">Or do we de facto accept Hamas’s position that peace between Israel and the Palestinians is not possible, and that peace talks therefore make no sense?</s>

<s sid="34">In that case, we would have to make do with organizing a truce until the next crisis.</s>

<s sid="35">But that would finally make any two-state solution a lost cause, and, although Hamas would have lost militarily, politically it would have won.</s>

<s sid="36" annotators="B C">The alternative to a two-state solution is continuation of the conflict and the de facto reality of a one-state solution in which Palestinians between the Jordan River and the Mediterranean will, sooner rather than later, constitute a majority.</s>

<s sid="37">For Israel and the Palestinians, this is a dire perspective from both a strategic and a humanitarian point of view.</s>

<s sid="38">Indeed, it is hopeless.</s>

<s sid="39" annotators="A C D">Trying to extricate both parties from the strategic dead-end into which they have maneuvered themselves will be possible only from outside.</s>

<s sid="40" annotators="B D">First, the United States must attempt to integrate Syria and Iran into a regional solution that also fundamentally changes conditions for both Israelis and Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="41" annotators="B D">Second, the US must impose a two-state solution on the parties involved, which will require both determination and maintaining the unity of the main international actors.</s>

<s sid="42" annotators="A C">If an imposed solution fails, the entire region will begin to slip into a dangerous confrontation during the first years of Barack Obama’s presidency.</s>

<s sid="43">And that confrontation will not be limited to Israelis and Palestinians.</s>

</document>

<document did="israel2" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/yehoshua6/English">

<s sid="1">Netanyahu’s Useless Demand</s>

<s sid="2">2009-06-22</s>

<s sid="3" annotators="A B C D">HAIFA – Ever since the Six Day War of June 1967, a small number of Israelis, not all on the left, supported the idea of two states as a solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</s>

<s sid="4">Most of their compatriots rejected it, as did the Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="5">Israelis justified their stance with this question: Just when did the Palestinians become a nation deserving of statehood?</s>

<s sid="6">The Palestinians were asking in return: Why should the Jews, a religious community dispersed around the world, have their own state?</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="A C">A lot of water had to pass under the bridge before the idea of a two-state solution, whether as a moral or a practical matter, began to filter into the Israeli and Palestinian political and ideological environments.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="C">People gradually became accustomed to the expression “Palestinian state,” and those who embraced it received support and gained prestige on the international scene.</s>

<s sid="9">After the Labor leaders Shimon Peres, Yitzhak Rabin, and Ehud Barak embraced the two-state concept, there came the first tentative movements in that direction from Likud members: Tzipi Livni, Ehud Olmert, and Ariel Sharon.</s>

<s sid="10">Now, from the very bastion of the right, came Benjamin Netanyahu.</s>

<s sid="11">We can congratulate ourselves: better late than never!</s>

<s sid="12" annotators="C">We are all aware that the road toward the realization of this dream is full of obstacles and difficulties, both on the Israeli and the Palestinian side.</s>

<s sid="13">I believe that some of the preconditions posed by the Israeli prime minister in his recent, widely reported speech are fully justified.</s>

<s sid="14">Others, however, are useless and only complicate further an already complex and problematic situation.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="A B C">Netanyahu’s demand that the future Palestinian state be demilitarized is just, reasonable, and necessary.</s>

<s sid="16">One look at a map is enough to understand this.</s>

<s sid="17">Even Egypt, a great and sovereign nation, accepted demilitarization of Sinai as a part of its peace process with Israel.</s>

<s sid="18">Indeed, demilitarization of Sinai is one of the fundamental elements of the stability of Egypt’s peace with Israel.</s>

<s sid="19">Other great and independent countries, such as Japan, Germany, and Austria, have been subjected for decades to limitations on their acquisition of certain weapons and military equipment.</s>

<s sid="20" annotators="A B C">Similarly, the refusal of Palestinian refugees’ claim to a right of return to Israel proper is understandable, logical, and just.</s>

<s sid="21">What sense would it make to bring back millions of Palestinians into a state whose character and symbols are foreign to them – a state where the majority belongs to another ethnic group?</s>

<s sid="22">Are they to go back to homes and farms that no longer exist?</s>

<s sid="23">These refugees could much more properly establish themselves in the new state of Palestine, their mother country, among their compatriots, under a Palestinian flag and Palestinian authority, merely 30 kilometers from the homes and farms that they abandoned, or from which they were expelled, more than 60 years ago.</s>

<s sid="24" annotators="A B C D">But the other condition demanded by Netanyahu, that the Palestinians recognize the right of the Jewish people to their own state, or the existence of the Jewish nation, is completely arbitrary.</s>

<s sid="25" annotators="D">In my opinion, it is superfluous to ask the Palestinians to recognize the nationhood of a people with thousands of years of history and a state that maintains diplomatic relations with 150 countries around the world.</s>

<s sid="26">A demand of this kind was not made of Egypt or Jordan when Israel signed peace agreements with those countries, and it constitutes an entirely useless obstacle on the road to peace with the Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="27" annotators="A B C">It will be more than sufficient to ask the Palestinians to recognize the legitimacy of the state of Israel, a state whose territorial boundaries and political identity are known to all.</s>

<s sid="28">On our part, we also will be recognizing not so much the Palestinian people, which one day may merge with the people of Jordan, as an independent and sovereign Palestinian state within the 1967 borders.</s>

<s sid="29">Framing the issue in this way makes sense for two reasons.</s>

<s sid="30" annotators="C">First, the question of Jewish nationality is, in fact, very complicated, even for Jews themselves, as many consider themselves Jewish only in a religious sense.</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="C">Second, the Palestinians’ refusal to recognize Israel as a Jewish state is motivated by, among other things, the presence of a Palestinian minority in Israel.</s>

<s sid="32">But relations between Israel’s Jewish majority and Arab minority is an internal, delicate question in which it is not wise to involve Palestinians outside of Israel.</s>

<s sid="33">For more than 60 years, the two groups have managed to live together in an acceptable manner, confronting with relative dignity the inferno of terrorism and the occupation of the West Bank and Gaza strip.</s>

<s sid="34">With the advent of peace, we all hope that this bond will become consolidated around a common Israeli citizenship.</s>

<s sid="35" annotators="D">There will be enough problems in negotiating the creation of a Palestinian state, so we should avoid adding other, gratuitous obstacles.</s>

<s sid="36" annotators="A B C D">Let’s focus on resolving the most important of the problems – demilitarization, settlements, borders, and refugees – and allow the reality of peace to leave behind, or postpone until the distant future, the solution of problems that are essentially historical and theological.</s>

</document>

<document did="israel4" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/rabbo1/English">

<s sid="1">Palestinian Hopes for Barack Obama</s>

<s sid="2">2008-11-14</s>

<s sid="3" annotators="B">RAMALLAH – President-elect Barack Obama’s defiantly positive campaign for change has inspired hope not only in the millions of Americans who voted for him, but also in the billions of others worldwide who could not.</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="B C">Across the Middle East, as elsewhere, expectations are building that his presidency will herald a new era for America’s role in the world.</s>

<s sid="5" annotators="A C">Palestinians identify strongly with the civil rights movement in the United States.</s>

<s sid="6">Many recall the dark days when American society enforced racial segregation.</s>

<s sid="7">That the same society elected an African-American president only a few decades later renews Palestinian hopes that, in our ongoing struggle for justice and freedom, we, too, shall overcome.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="B">Obama’s electoral triumph arrives at a symbolic moment in Palestinian history.</s>

<s sid="9" annotators="B">This month marks the twentieth anniversary of the Palestinian Declaration of Independence.</s>

<s sid="10">Drafted by the poetic hand of my late friend, Mahmoud Darwish, the text is nothing short of visionary.</s>

<s sid="11" annotators="A D">Whereas previously the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) had campaigned for a single, secular, and democratic state across the entirety of mandatory Palestine, our Declaration of Independence endorsed a two-state solution.</s>

<s sid="12">The depth of this compromise can be fully appreciated only in its historical context.</s>

<s sid="13">In the war and violence that surrounded Israel’s establishment in 1948, our losses were immense.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="C">Over 726,000 Palestinian Christians and Muslims – the majority of the Arab population of mandatory Palestine – fled or were forced to leave their homes by Zionist militias.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="C">Over 400 Palestinian villages in what became Israel were destroyed or depopulated.</s>

<s sid="16" annotators="A C D">Endorsing a two-state solution meant recognizing Israeli sovereignty over 78% of our homeland and exercising our right to self-determination on only the remaining 22% that Israel has occupied militarily since 1967: the West Bank, including East Jerusalem, and the Gaza Strip.</s>

<s sid="17">Yet we made this historic compromise because we believed that doing so would bring us to the threshold of liberty.</s>

<s sid="18">Of course, that is not how things have turned out: Palestinians have been living under Israeli occupation for 41 years.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="A">As Obama prepares to enter the White House, we are confident that he will consider the constructive role America can play in the search for peace and security.</s>

<s sid="20">In the year since Palestinians and Israelis renewed their commitment to their obligations under the “road map,” we may have failed to reach a conclusive settlement to our conflict, but that does not mean that the efforts made were in vain.</s>

<s sid="21">With the determination of both sides, I am confident that we can reach a final agreement in relatively short order.</s>

<s sid="22" annotators="B D">The US can take four practical steps to help negotiations move forward immediately.</s>

<s sid="23" annotators="B C D">The first step is early engagement.</s>

<s sid="24">The Bush administration’s efforts to assist our peace-making project faltered in part because our conflict was neglected during the early part of its tenure.</s>

<s sid="25">Allowing this conflict to fester will only aggravate our peoples’ insecurity and our region’s instability.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="A B C D">Second, the US should establish a credible enforcement mechanism to ensure that the parties comply with their respective obligations, particularly an immediate freeze on Israeli settlement activity throughout the occupied Palestinian territory.</s>

<s sid="27">Not only has Israel failed to halt its settlement activity since Annapolis – in violation of international law and its renewed road map commitments – but it has actually accelerated such activity.</s>

<s sid="28">Construction of settlement housing units is over 45% higher now than in the nine months prior to Annapolis.</s>

<s sid="29">Israeli demolitions of Palestinian homes have also increased, particularly in occupied East Jerusalem.</s>

<s sid="30">Nothing undermines Palestinian faith in the peace process like watching the homes of our families flattened, while the architecture of our oppression is strengthened.</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="A B C D">Third, the new administration should encourage the re-engagement of its Quartet partners – the United Nations, the European Union, and Russia – in the mediation process.</s>

<s sid="32">International cooperation is key to securing the legitimacy of negotiations, and it will be critical when the time comes for the enforcement and implementation of any agreement.</s>

<s sid="33">The US cannot be expected to shoulder the post-conflict burdens of peacekeeping alone.</s>

<s sid="34" annotators="A B C D">Fourth, the US should renew its respect for international law by recognizing three principles: that the 1967 pre-occupation boundaries must be respected in any negotiations; that Palestinian sovereignty over East Jerusalem must be safeguarded, with guaranteed access for Muslims, Christians, and Jews to their holy sites; and that the plight of Palestinian refugees, whose 60-year ordeal remains emblematic of the Palestinian predicament, must be acknowledged and fairly addressed.</s>

<s sid="35">Fortunately, a framework already exists that supports these concerns.</s>

<s sid="36" annotators="A C">The 2002 Arab Peace Initiative offers Israel a unique opportunity: full normalization of relations with 57 Arab and Muslim states in return for a comprehensive peace agreement, including an end to Israel’s occupation of Arab lands and a just and agreed upon solution for refugees.</s>

<s sid="37">Our Declaration of Independence is now twenty years old.</s>

<s sid="38">The Arab Peace Initiative has been collecting dust for over six years.</s>

<s sid="39">Palestinian patience is not infinite.</s>

<s sid="40">Some have already resigned themselves to believing a viable Palestinian state will never emerge.</s>

<s sid="41">Others, like me, argue that we must not lose faith.</s>

<s sid="42">But if we are to realize our dream of freedom and statehood -and prove the cynics wrong- we will need President Obama’s help.</s>

</document>

<document did="israel3" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/benami34/English">

<s sid="1">The Return of 1948</s>

<s sid="2">2009-10-05</s>

<s sid="3">TEL AVIV – The forthcoming United Nation’s conference commemorating the 60th anniversary of UNRWA (The UN Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees) could not come at a better moment.</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="A B C D">The restitution of lands occupied in 1967 will obviously continue to be indispensable to resolving the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, but it is the legacy of the 1948 war that both parties to the conflict have now put at the center of the debate.</s>

<s sid="5" annotators="A B">Oddly, it was Israeli Prime Minister Binyamin Netanyahu who, by requesting that the Palestinians recognize Israel as a Jewish state, reopened the 1948 file.</s>

<s sid="6">That demand brought the quest for peace back to its fundamentals, where the question of the refugees is bound to play a central role.</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="B C">Netanyahu’s intention was essentially to force the Palestinians into admitting that the right of return of refugees applies only to the Palestinian state, not Israel.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="B">But the true significance of his demand lies in that it’s being pronounced at a time when Prime Minister Salam Fayaad’s policies are posing a genuine challenge to the Palestinian national movement to choose between an ethos of vindication and one of state building.</s>

<s sid="9" annotators="B C">Under Fayaad, the Palestinian Authority seems to be superseding the Palestinian national movement’s diaspora-based emphasis in favor of state-building within the territorial confines of the occupied territories.</s>

<s sid="10">It is as if the voice of the diaspora were being silenced in Palestine.</s>

<s sid="11">Conspicuously, the recently elected PLO Executive Committee – which in the past consisted exclusively of representatives of the Palestinian Diaspora – now has only one member from the diaspora, a delegate from Lebanon.</s>

<s sid="12">This could mark a sea change in the evolution of Palestinian nationalism.</s>

<s sid="13" annotators="B">In Zionism, the Jewish community in Palestine was the focus of decision making, with the Jewish Diaspora a strategic back-up.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="B">But the situation was reversed in the case of the Palestinians: the ethos of the diaspora, with the plight of the refugees at its center, has been the beating heart of the Palestinian cause and the focus of decision making for the national movement.</s>

<s sid="15">As a result, the Palestinian community in the occupied territories was always subservient to the primacy of the Palestinian Diaspora.</s>

<s sid="16">When it sought to assume a leading role – during the first Intifada in 1987, for example, its effort was suppressed by the diaspora-based PLO.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="C">Fayaadism, by contrast, seeks the “Zionization” of the Palestinian national movement.</s>

<s sid="18">It imbues the Palestinian cause with a positive ethos of nation- and state-building by superseding Palestinian nationalism’s diaspora-centered preoccupations – and thereby transcending the paralyzing obsession with a never-fulfilled vindication of rights and justice.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="A C D">In the peace process as it has been conducted up to now, the Israelis always wanted to concentrate on the issues of 1967 – that is, land and security.</s>

<s sid="20" annotators="A B C D">The Palestinians, however, always wanted to return to the issues of 1948: refugees, dispersion, and what Akram Hanya, a close Arafat confidant, defined as the need “to make the Israelis face the tribunal of history.”</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="D">It looks as if now the roles have been inversed.</s>

<s sid="22" annotators="B">Precisely when Israel managed to domesticate the Palestinian national movement by forcing it to abandon its revolutionary path in favor of state-building and economic development – a reorientation undertaken by Zionism as well – the Israelis decided to draw the Palestinians back to the fundamentals of the conflict.</s>

<s sid="23" annotators="C">Indeed, despite of the rise of Fayaadism, the Palestinian national movement will be careful not to betray its real sources of legitimacy: the ethos of dispossession and the refugee.</s>

<s sid="24">The decisions taken at the last Fatah Convention were explicit in calling for the refugees to “return to their homes and cities.”</s>

<s sid="25" annotators="A C">The Palestinians are attempting to hold the stick at both ends, claiming before the world their endorsement of the two-state solution while calling for the right of return at the same time.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="B">Any sober Palestinian leadership must know by now that the rhetorical promise of a return to an abandoned house and to the olive tree is an irresponsible mirage that fundamentally contradicts the rationale for a separate Palestinian state.</s>

<s sid="27">Peace is frequently not about justice but about stability.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="C D">The Palestinians must align their national conversation with what is realizable, while Israel must resolve its own contradictions and address the refugee problem in a way that secures the legitimacy and durability of a future peace agreement with the Palestinians.</s>

<s sid="29">Because Israel will have to implement practical measures of resettlement and compensation that will not be based on an automatic right of physical return, a symbol of genuine moral compensation is also called for.</s>

<s sid="30" annotators="C">Instead of suppressing the memory of the refugees, Israel needs to recognize that in 1948 the land was bisected by the sword, and that the Jewish state came into being partly because of the massive uprooting and dispossession of Palestinian communities.</s>

<s sid="31">Israel should develop enough self-confidence in its solidity as a nation to integrate into its schools’ curriculum the tragedy of the Palestinian Naqbah.</s>

<s sid="32" annotators="A B">The resolution of conflicts of this nature requires the recovery of historical memory and a proper hearing of the two parties’ historical narratives, perhaps through the creation of Truth and Reconciliation Committees.</s>

<s sid="33">Israel’s consolation would be that the Palestinians, too, will have to come to terms with their share of responsibility for the calamities that have befallen them.</s>

<s sid="34" annotators="A D">Only an acceptable deal on the refugees can definitely close the 1948 file – and only then can the conflict in Palestine end.</s>

</document>

<document did="israel5" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/yaghi1/English">

<s sid="1">Will Hamas Win the Peace?</s>

<s sid="2">2009-01-19</s>

<s sid="3" annotators="B">WASHINGTON, DC –For generations to come, the Palestinians will remember the horrific war in Gaza with pain and bitterness.</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="B">But what cannot yet be seen is how Palestinians will view Hamas.</s>

<s sid="5" annotators="A C D">Whether Hamas can claim a victory – and whether Palestinians will believe them will be determined by the type of ceasefire that is eventually agreed, if a formal one is eventually agreed.</s>

<s sid="6">The end game – for both Israel and Hamas – is thus crucially important.</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="C D">For the moment, Hamas is perceived by the majority of Palestinians as the victim of a war intended to gain its surrender.</s>

<s sid="8">After all, Hamas was democratically elected, but was forbidden from ruling and besieged in Gaza.</s>

<s sid="9" annotators="D">At the same time, Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas is accused of siding with Israel in order to restore his lost authority in Gaza.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="B">The war exposed flaws in Hamas’ judgment.</s>

<s sid="11" annotators="B C">Hamas apparently did not envision a full-scale confrontation with Israel when it refused to renew a six-month truce.</s>

<s sid="12">With Gaza suffering under a lengthy siege, Hamas leader Khalid Mashal said that there was no point in a new truce, since the old one had “failed to lift the siege on Gaza.” Other leaders were quoted as saying that Hamas would “lift the siege by force.”</s>

<s sid="13" annotators="D">If Hamas is to survive the war, it must demonstrate that its resistance resulted in a permanent opening of Gaza’s border crossings, especially in Rafah.</s>

<s sid="14">For Palestinians, these are signs of victory.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="A C">With open borders, Hamas would secure its regime in Gaza and build its popularity in the West Bank, putting enormous pressure on Abbas, the leader of the rival Fatah movement, to accept a national unity government on terms set by Hamas.</s>

<s sid="16">Members of Fatah’s Central Committee are already accusing Abbas of supporting Israel in the fighting, of wanting to “return to Gaza on an Israeli tank.” Radical groups within Fatah are leaning toward an open alliance with Hamas.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="D">If Hamas comes out ahead, Abbas’s allies in other Palestinian factions will press him to accept Hamas and Islamic Jihad within the PLO.</s>

<s sid="18">Egypt will have to backtrack on its rejection of Hamas in order to recover its image among the Arabs and to reduce tensions within Egyptian society.</s>

<s sid="19">Pressure to integrate Hamas into Palestinian politics is also likely in some European capitals, particularly Paris and London, where some expressed opposition to isolating Hamas even before the war.</s>

<s sid="20" annotators="A B C D">But if Israel forces Hamas to accept its conditions for border controls and a formal ceasefire, Hamas’s image as the guardian of Palestinian resistance will be severely damaged.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="B">Palestinians will ask if it was really necessary to fight this war and pay such a high price.</s>

<s sid="22" annotators="B">Abbas will be able to argue that he advised Hamas to renew the truce and to end its missile fire on Israeli towns, but that Hamas insisted on exposing Palestinian civilians to devastation.</s>

<s sid="23" annotators="B C">One indicator to watch for: the length of that ceasefire.</s>

<s sid="24" annotators="B">Palestinians will recognize Hamas’s acceptance of a multi-year truce with Israel as a sign of defeat, which would also underscore Palestinian feelings of humiliation and abandonment.</s>

<s sid="25">Hezbollah, despite its rhetoric, has taken no steps to support Hamas, and the Arab states seemed more than willing to support its defeat.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="A">It is in rebuilding Gaza that the stakes of the competition will increase.</s>

<s sid="27" annotators="A C">Abbas, supported by the United States and the European Union, may have control over significant funding.</s>

<s sid="28">The test for him will be to deliver quickly.</s>

<s sid="29" annotators="C">Hamas will also have resources for reconstruction.</s>

<s sid="30" annotators="A">Qatar, a Hamas supporter, has already announced an investment fund for Gaza and contributed $250 million.</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="C">Hamas will have to make a convincing case that Gaza’s near destruction is a price that had to be paid.</s>

<s sid="32">Many Palestinians believe that Israel inflicted this damage on Gaza to drive a wedge between the people and the “resistance.” There is a precedent for this argument: Hezbollah described the destruction of Beirut’s southern suburbs in exactly these terms at the end of the Lebanon War in July 2006.</s>

<s sid="33">More importantly, Hamas can demonstrate that its leaders have been on the front lines during this war, sharing Palestinian suffering; many have been killed, along with their families.</s>

<s sid="34" annotators="C">The biggest question is whether the war will alter Hamas’ political goals.</s>

<s sid="35">Two weeks ago, Musa Abu Marzouk, a senior Hamas official, praised Jimmy Carter in The Los Angeles Times as the only American president who had brought true peace in the Middle East.</s>

<s sid="36">This is a radical departure from Hamas rhetoric, which has always portrayed the Camp David agreement between Israel and Egypt as a betrayal of the Islamic world.</s>

<s sid="37" annotators="A C">It remains to be seen whether Abu Marzouk’s view is merely a tactic intended to encourage the Obama administration to reach out to Hamas, or whether the war convinced Hamas that the two-state solution is the only viable option to settle the conflict with Israel.</s>

</document>

</cluster>