<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<cluster cid="Malaria" lang="English">

<document did="malaria3" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/achmat1/English">

<s sid="1">﻿The Time is Now to Fight Disease</s>

<s sid="2">Mabel van Oranje and Zackie Achmat</s>

<s sid="3">2005-03-14</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="B D">It is possible for a child born just ten years from now to live in a world where AIDS, tuberculosis and malaria are on the wane.</s>

<s sid="5">But this can only happen with considerable investment.</s>

<s sid="6">Now.</s>

<s sid="7">Otherwise, today’s grim picture will only get worse.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="C D">Each day, these diseases kill 16,000 people—devastating entire communities and plummeting countries deeper into poverty.</s>

<s sid="9">Upping the ante could turn the tables.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="A B C">Recent successes in Brazil against AIDS, in Mozambique against malaria, and in China against TB, show what can be achieved on a global scale with more resources.</s>

<s sid="11">There are new ways of directing aid to where it is most needed.</s>

<s sid="12" annotators="A D">A key instrument is the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, TB and Malaria.</s>

<s sid="13" annotators="B">Created in 2002 as a partnership between governments and civil society, the Global Fund is unique in the way it aims to deliver assistance.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="C">Driven by real needs on the ground, projects are designed and implemented by recipients, and its procedures and operations are transparent.</s>

<s sid="15">Of late there has been much talk about intensifying efforts to eradicate poverty.</s>

<s sid="16">Ahead of the G8 summit in Scotland in July, a coalition of non-governmental organizations has launched the “Global Call to Action Against Poverty,” and the UK host has made Africa a top priority.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="C">Building on this momentum, the campaigns for debt relief, trade reform, and increasing aid to poor countries have gained traction.</s>

<s sid="18" annotators="C">Yet, while pledges to increase development assistance have soared, short-term funding is woefully inadequate.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="C D">Any strategy for raising living standards must include urgent measures that address AIDS, TB and malaria.</s>

<s sid="20">Stemming the spread of this deadly trio of diseases is the linchpin in the global fight against poverty.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="C">Unchecked, these diseases not only sap the strength of national economies, but jeopardize peace and security.</s>

<s sid="22">Teachers and nurses are dying; police and security forces are being hard hit, and 14 million children have already been orphaned by AIDS.</s>

<s sid="23">We now risk failing to meet the Millennium Development GOAL, set out by the United Nations, of reversing the spread of AIDS, TB and malaria by 2015.</s>

<s sid="24">This failure will make remote any hope of reaching the other Millennium goals in the fight against poverty.</s>

<s sid="25">A comprehensive response to AIDS, TB and malaria is needed.</s>

<s sid="26">Acting now means less spending in the long run.</s>

<s sid="27" annotators="A B C D">Investments in effective prevention, treatment and research in 2005 and 2006 will save millions of lives, lessen the socio-economic impact of the diseases in poorer countries, and remove the need for increased spending on these chronic crises in the future.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="A B D">The Global Fund plays an important role in this funding environment, providing approximately 66% of all current external funds in the fight against TB, 45% in the fight against malaria, and 20% of all external support to combat HIV/AIDS.</s>

<s sid="29">Since the Global Fund was founded three years ago, it has built an impressive track record: approving 310 grants totaling $3.1 billion in 127 countries and disbursing $920 million since 2002.</s>

<s sid="30">Despite the scope of its mission, it has a minimal bureaucracy, which allows for a flexible response to changing needs.</s>

<s sid="31">The Global Fund is not perfect; as with all new organizations, it is experiencing growing pains.</s>

<s sid="32">Yet, issues such as procurement policies, trade-offs between efficiency and ownership, and the balance between government and non-governmental organizations as implementing partners are being addressed through the Fund’s open and inclusive governance systems.</s>

<s sid="33" annotators="D">If the Fund is to live up to its potential it will need $2.3 billion to continue its work effectively in 2005.</s>

<s sid="34">The first of two replenishment conferences for the Global Fund is taking place this week in Stockholm, with the aim of securing financial pledges to cover grant commitments in 2006-2007, as well as to fill the gap for this year.</s>

<s sid="35">Donors have long preached the importance of a funding vehicle such as the Global Fund—one that is needs-driven, relies on local input, and promotes donor coordination.</s>

<s sid="36">They now have a chance to make good on their word.</s>

<s sid="37" annotators="C">With many battles ahead in the fight against AIDS, TB and malaria, it would be a disgrace if this opportunity is squandered.</s>

</document>

<document did="malaria4" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/lomborg10/English">

<s sid="1">﻿Live Earth, Deaf to Reality</s>

<s sid="2">Bjørn Lomborg</s>

<s sid="3">2007-07-02</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="B">The organizers of next Saturday’s Live Earth concerts hope that the entire world will hear a crystal clear message: climate change is the most critical threat facing the planet.</s>

<s sid="5">Planned by former US Vice President Al Gore, Live Earth will be the biggest, most mass-marketed show of celebrity activism in history.</s>

<s sid="6" annotators="C">But making global warming the world’s top priority means that we shuffle other major challenges down our “to do” list.</s>

<s sid="7">Some climate change activists actually acknowledge this: Australian author Tim Flannery recently told an interviewer that climate change is “the only issue we should worry about for the next decade.”</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="B C">Tell that to the four million people starving to death, to the three million victims of HIV/AIDS, or to the billions of people who lack access to clean drinking water.</s>

<s sid="9" annotators="D">Human-caused climate change deserves attention – and it has gotten it, thanks to Gore, Flannery, and others.</s>

<s sid="10">Even before a single note has been played in the “awareness-raising” concerts, much of the developed world believes that global warming is the planet’s biggest problem.</s>

<s sid="11">Yet, the world faces many other vast challenges.</s>

<s sid="12">Whether we like it or not, we have limited money and a limited attention span for global causes.</s>

<s sid="13">We should focus first on achieving the most good for the most people.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="B">The Copenhagen Consensus project brought together top-class thinkers, including four Nobel Laureate economists, to examine what we could achieve with a $50 billion investment designed to “do good” for the planet.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="B D">They examined the best research available and concluded that projects requiring a relatively small investment – getting micro-nutrients to those suffering from malnutrition, providing more resources for HIV/AIDS prevention, making a proper effort to get drinking water to those who lack it – would do far more good than the billions of dollars we could spend reducing carbon emissions to combat climate change.</s>

<s sid="16">Carbon reduction activists argue that focusing exclusively on climate change will bring many benefits.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="A C D">They point out, for example, that malaria deaths will climb along with temperatures, because potentially killer mosquitoes thrive in warmer areas.</s>

<s sid="18">And they would be right.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="C">But it’s not as simple as the bumper sticker slogan “Fight climate change and ward off malaria.”</s>

<s sid="20">If America and Australia are somehow inspired by the Live Earth concerts to sign the Kyoto Protocol, temperatures would rise by slightly less.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="C">The number of people at risk of malaria would be reduced by about 0.2% by 2085.</s>

<s sid="22">Yet the cost of the Kyoto Protocol would be a staggering $180 billion a year.</s>

<s sid="23">In other words, climate change campaigners believe we should spend $180 billion to save just 1,000 lives a year.</s>

<s sid="24">For much less money, we could save 850,000 lives each and every year.</s>

<s sid="25" annotators="A B C D">We know that dissemination of mosquito nets and malaria prevention programs could cut malaria incidence in half by 2015 for about $3 billion annually – less than 2% of the cost of Kyoto.</s>

<s sid="26">The choice is stark.</s>

<s sid="27">Some will argue that the real problem is that the Kyoto Protocol isn’t strong enough.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="D">But, as I point out in my forthcoming book Cool It, even if we could stop global warming right now – which is impossible – we could reduce malaria infections by only 3.2% by 2085.</s>

<s sid="29">Should we not worry more about the 100% infected now, whom we can help much better, more cheaply, and with much greater effect?</s>

<s sid="30">When we look at the evidence, we discover again and again that the best solutions to the world’s biggest challenges aren’t the ones we hear about the most.</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="D">We could save many more lives during extreme weather events, for example, by insisting on hurricane-resistant building standards than we would by committing to Live Earth’s target of a 90% reduction in carbon emissions by 2050.</s>

<s sid="32">This would be easier, much less costly, and ultimately do far more good.</s>

<s sid="33" annotators="B">Indeed, the Copenhagen Consensus experts discovered that for every dollar invested in Kyoto-style battling climate change, we could do up to 120 times more good with in numerous other areas.</s>

<s sid="34">It’s honorable that the Live Earth organizers are so concerned about the far-off future, but you have to wonder why there is so little concern about the much-worse present.</s>

<s sid="35">I don’t want to stop anyone from caring about climate change, only to encourage a sense of perspective.</s>

<s sid="36" annotators="C D">There is a massive amount of good that we can do through practical, affordable approaches like HIV/AIDS education, malaria prevention, and the provision of micro-nutrients or clean water.</s>

<s sid="37">This is the message I would like to ring out: we should focus on the best ideas first.</s>

<s sid="38">This Saturday, unfortunately, that is not what we’ll hear.</s>

</document>

<document did="malaria9" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/lomborg54/English">

<s sid="1">﻿Global Warming’s Misunderstood Victims</s>

<s sid="2">Bjørn Lomborg</s>

<s sid="3">2009-11-12</s>

<s sid="4">BAMAKO, MALI – Media organizations in wealthy countries regularly send forth reporters to find “victims of global warming.” In dispatches from the Pacific Islands, Bangladesh, or Ethiopia, journalists warn of impending calamity.</s>

<s sid="5" annotators="B">Global warming is the most horrific challenge facing these regions, we are told.</s>

<s sid="6">Its resolution is vital.</s>

<s sid="7">But seldom do we hear from the local people who are said to be in danger.</s>

<s sid="8">These people are not voiceless; we just pay no attention to what they say.</s>

<s sid="9" annotators="B">The Copenhagen Consensus Center set out to ask people in global-warming hot spots about their fears and hopes.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="B">In Mojo, central Ethiopia, our researchers met Tadese Denkue, a 68-year-old former soldier with no regular income.</s>

<s sid="11">“I never know when I will be able to buy myself some food,” he said.</s>

<s sid="12">“I only know that I suffer a lot.</s>

<s sid="13">This is not a decent life.”</s>

<s sid="14">Tadese has never heard of global warming.</s>

<s sid="15">When it is explained to him, he is dismissive.</s>

<s sid="16" annotators="B">He has more immediate concerns: “The first thing I need is food, and then a job.”</s>

<s sid="17">Tadese is suffering from his second bout of malaria this year.</s>

<s sid="18">He has lost count of how many times he has contracted the disease.</s>

<s sid="19">Our researcher accompanies him to a free clinic.</s>

<s sid="20">The electricity is not working.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="C">A doctor admits that most patients are sent home without testing or treatment: the clinic has run out of medicine.</s>

<s sid="22" annotators="A B">The threat of more malaria has been used to argue for drastic carbon cuts.</s>

<s sid="23" annotators="A">Warmer, wetter weather will improve conditions for the malaria parasite.</s>

<s sid="24" annotators="A C D">Most estimates suggest that global warming will put 3% more of the earth’s population at risk of catching malaria by 2100.</s>

<s sid="25" annotators="A B">The most efficient, global carbon cuts – designed to keep temperature increases under two degrees Celsius – would cost $40 trillion a year by 2100, according to research by Richard Tol for the Copenhagen Consensus Center.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="A">In the best-case scenario, this expenditure would reduce the at-risk population by only 3%.</s>

<s sid="27" annotators="A B C D">In comparison, spending $3 billion annually on mosquito nets, environmentally safe indoor DDT sprays, and subsidies for effective new combination therapies could halve the total number of those infected within one decade.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="A B">For the money it takes to save one life with carbon cuts, smarter policies could save 78,000 lives.</s>

<s sid="29" annotators="D">Of course, malaria is far from the only reason we worry about global warming.</s>

<s sid="30" annotators="B">Twenty kilometers from Mojo, our researcher met Desi Koricho and her eight-month-old son, Michel.</s>

<s sid="31">Every two weeks, Desi walks four hours to take Michel to the health center.</s>

<s sid="32" annotators="B">After two months of malnutrition treatment, Michel has grown a lot but remains half the normal size of a baby his age.</s>

<s sid="33">Michel is not Desi’s biological child.</s>

<s sid="34">She took him in after his father committed suicide and he was abandoned.</s>

<s sid="35">Desi likely suffers from undiagnosed malnutrition herself.</s>

<s sid="36">It is rife here.</s>

<s sid="37">There are no roads, electricity, or other infrastructure.</s>

<s sid="38">Conditions are cramped and unhygienic.</s>

<s sid="39">“We need everything,” Desi says.</s>

<s sid="40" annotators="B">Solving the malnutrition challenge would be a good start.</s>

<s sid="41" annotators="B">Campaigners across Europe and the US use the threat of starvation to argue for drastic carbon cuts.</s>

<s sid="42">For most regions, weather changes will increase agricultural productivity.</s>

<s sid="43">Cruelly, this is not the case for parts of Africa that are already suffering from hunger.</s>

<s sid="44" annotators="B C">But, as with malaria, all of the evidence shows that direct policies are much more effective than carbon cuts.</s>

<s sid="45">One effective, under-appreciated intervention is providing micro-nutrients to those who lack them.</s>

<s sid="46" annotators="B">Providing Vitamin A and zinc to 80% of the 140 million or so undernourished children in the world would require a commitment of just $60 million annually.</s>

<s sid="47" annotators="B">For $286 million, we could get iron and iodine to more than 2.5 billion people.</s>

<s sid="48" annotators="D">The choice is stark: for a few hundred million dollars, we could help almost half of humanity now.</s>

<s sid="49" annotators="B">Compare this to the investments to tackle climate change – $40 trillion annually by the end of the century – which would save a hundred times fewer starving people (and in 90 years!).</s>

<s sid="50" annotators="C">For every person saved from malnutrition through climate policies, the same money could have saved half a million people from micronutrient malnutrition through direct policies.</s>

<s sid="51">Some argue that the choice between spending money on carbon cuts and on direct policies is unfair.</s>

<s sid="52">But it is a basic fact that no dollar can be spent twice.</s>

<s sid="53">Rich countries and donors have limited budgets and attention spans.</s>

<s sid="54" annotators="C D">If we spend vast amounts of money on carbon cuts in the mistaken belief that we are stopping malaria and reducing malnutrition, we are less likely to put aside money for the direct policies that would help today.</s>

<s sid="55">Indeed, for every dollar spent on strong climate policies, we will likely do about $0.02 of good for the future.</s>

<s sid="56" annotators="C">If we spent the same dollar on simple policies to help malnutrition or malaria now, we could do $20 or more good – 1000 times better, when all impacts are taken into account.</s>

<s sid="57" annotators="B">On Mount Kilimanjaro in Tanzania – where the effects of global warming can already be felt – our researcher encountered 28-year-old Rehema Ibrahim.</s>

<s sid="58">Rehema was divorced by her husband and disowned by her family after she failed to produce children.</s>

<s sid="59">To find out if she was the cause of the infertility, she started sleeping with other men.</s>

<s sid="60">She is now HIV-positive, an outcast in a terribly poor society.</s>

<s sid="61">Rehema has noticed changes in the weather.</s>

<s sid="62">She says that the snow and ice have been melting.</s>

<s sid="63" annotators="B">She knows what our researcher means by “global warming.” But, she says: “The issues I am experiencing have greater priority.</s>

<s sid="64" annotators="B">The HIV and the problems it is causing are greater than the [receding] ice.”</s>

<s sid="65">Campaigners for carbon-emission reductions regularly highlight the melting snow and ice of Mount Kilimanjaro.</s>

<s sid="66">But we need to pay as much attention to the people living in the mountain’s shadow.</s>

</document>

<document did="malaria1" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/sachs118/English">

<s sid="1">﻿Getting Practical in Controlling Malaria</s>

<s sid="2">Jeffrey D. Sachs</s>

<s sid="3">2006-12-20</s>

<s sid="4" annotators="D">Many international assistance programs fail because they are badly designed and/or too complicated.</s>

<s sid="5">The result is that the poor don’t get the help they need, and taxpayers in rich countries lose confidence in the use of their aid funds.</s>

<s sid="6">A case in point has been malaria control.</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="A B C">If rich countries adopt simpler and more practical strategies to help Africa fight malaria, they can save millions of Africans while building enthusiastic support among their citizens.</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="C D">Malaria is a killer disease transmitted by a specific species of mosquitoes.</s>

<s sid="9">It depends on warm temperatures, and thus is largely a tropical malady.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="A B">Africa turns out to be especially unlucky, because it has a combination of high temperatures and the mosquitos that are likely to transmit the disease.</s>

<s sid="11" annotators="A B">As a result, Africa accounts for 90% of all malaria deaths in the world – including roughly two million children per year.</s>

<s sid="12">Yet even in Africa, Malaria is largely preventable and completely treatable at low cost.</s>

<s sid="13">Up until now, there has been far too little malaria control.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="A B C D">Prevention is best accomplished by modern anti-malaria bed nets, which are treated with insecticide.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="C">These nets cover people while they sleep, and repel or kill the mosquitoes, which tend to bite during the night.</s>

<s sid="16">The nets reduce the number of bites, and the amount of illness, but they do not eliminate them.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="B">If people get bitten despite the nets, they require treatment within a few hours of the onset of symptoms.</s>

<s sid="18">There are two major obstacles to solving the malaria problem.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="A B C">First, Africa’s poor cannot afford insecticide-treated bed nets and the correct medicines.</s>

<s sid="20">Many end up taking cheap medicines that are not effective because the malaria parasite has developed resistance to them.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="A B C">Second, African villagers lack access to cars or trucks, so they have to walk several miles to reach a clinic.</s>

<s sid="22">An infected child is often dead or comatose by the time a mother reaches a clinic.</s>

<s sid="23" annotators="A D">If rich-country governments thought practically about malaria and recognized that it is a full-scale emergency, they could support simple and practical solutions: bed nets and timely access to medicine.</s>

<s sid="24" annotators="C">Rich countries would buy bed nets from companies that produce them and work with African governments to distribute them free of charge to every African household.</s>

<s sid="25">And they would work with African governments to ensure that the correct medicines are available for quick use within each village.</s>

<s sid="26" annotators="B">There are one billion people living in rich donor countries, and the total cost of comprehensive malaria control in Africa – giving bed nets at no cost to all Africans, and providing the right medicines within every village – is around $2.5 billion per year, or just $2.50 per citizen of the rich countries.</s>

<s sid="27">But the rich countries have instead adopted failed strategies.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="B C">Rather than giving away bed nets, rich-country organizations like the United States Agency for International Development try to sell them to the extreme poor, albeit at heavily discounted prices.</s>

<s sid="29">This policy reflects a shortsighted ambition to promote markets rather than the direct and over-riding goals of saving lives and removing bottlenecks to long-term economic development.</s>

<s sid="30" annotators="B">The tragic result has been extremely low use of nets throughout most of Africa, since impoverished people lack the purchasing power to buy nets.</s>

<s sid="31" annotators="B">Second, donor governments have failed to promote simple ways to ensure the availability of medicines in villages across the continent.</s>

<s sid="32" annotators="C">Rather than shipping medicines to each country on the basis of estimated needs, donor agencies have set up a complicated purchasing system that has led to years of delay in getting medicines to the villages.</s>

<s sid="33">The pharmaceutical industry, led by Novartis, has been way ahead of donor agencies.</s>

<s sid="34">Novartis has agreed to make these medicines available at the cost of production.</s>

<s sid="35">But, despite Novartis’s large production capacity, donor agencies have failed to order, buy, and ship the medicines in the required amounts.</s>

<s sid="36">Malaria control now faces a period of increasing urgency, as well as renewed hope.</s>

<s sid="37" annotators="A C D">Malaria is spreading, and new scientific evidence indicates that people infected with HIV are more likely to transmit it to others when they are also infected with malaria.</s>

<s sid="38">But there is also a growing realization that malaria is a disaster that must be addressed.</s>

<s sid="39">US President George W. Bush has launched an important new initiative to help 15 African countries to control malaria, and hosted an unprecedented White House summit in December to rally private-sector support.</s>

<s sid="40">Similarly, the Chinese government, the World Bank, and the Islamic Development Bank have recently announced plans to scale up their contributions to the fight against malaria.</s>

<s sid="41">A major new citizens’ initiative called Malaria No More is raising private funds to distribute anti-malaria nets.</s>

<s sid="42">People across Africa have shown that they are ready to mobilize their efforts if we offer practical means to help them.</s>

<s sid="43" annotators="C D">The world’s safety, including the safety of people living in rich countries, depends on the global community’s ability to prove that it will come to the aid of all who are in desperate need.</s>

<s sid="44">Aid can work wonders if it is practical and directed to those in need.</s>

<s sid="45">Malaria control can demonstrate this world-saving lesson once again.</s>

</document>

<document did="malaria2" url="http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/feachem1/English">

<s sid="1">﻿Marginalizing Malaria</s>

<s sid="2">Richard Feachem</s>

<s sid="3">2008-09-24</s>

<s sid="4">SAN FRANCISCO – Last fall, Bill and Melinda Gates sent shock waves through the global health community when they announced the audacious goal of eradicating human malaria from the face of the planet.</s>

<s sid="5">Nothing less, they urged, would be enough.</s>

<s sid="6">Heated debate immediately erupted, with some experienced practitioners questioning the feasibility of such a goal.</s>

<s sid="7" annotators="A">These skeptics pointed to the first Global Eradication Program, an ambitious effort in the 1950’s to clear malaria from many areas of the world (Africa was excluded).</s>

<s sid="8" annotators="A C">Despite initial progress, eradication programs crumbled as donors, governments, and populations grew tired and turned their attention elsewhere, allowing malaria to resurge to devastating levels.</s>

<s sid="9">No one is suggesting a return to the failed strategies of the first eradication program.</s>

<s sid="10" annotators="A">The Gates Foundation has sensibly begun to facilitate consultations with leading scientists on accelerating the development of potent new tools, and is already funding the development of a vaccine, as well as new drugs and diagnostics.</s>

<s sid="11">At the same time, the Roll Back Malaria Partnership has recently launched a long-term Global Action Plan to unify the actions of the malaria community and spur additional investment.</s>

<s sid="12" annotators="D">All agree that eradication is decades away.</s>

<s sid="13" annotators="C D">Yet, while total eradication is beyond the horizon, and new tools are needed to get there, there is much that can be achieved in the near term with our current armory.</s>

<s sid="14" annotators="A B C D">Recent success in countries such as Ethiopia and Rwanda in expanding access to impregnated bed nets and slashing malaria rates is building confidence that the disease can be dramatically reduced around the world and, in some areas, eliminated entirely.</s>

<s sid="15" annotators="B">To realize this opportunity, a sound strategy must rapidly be developed and executed.</s>

<s sid="16">In a recent article in the British scientific journal The Lancet, Oliver Sabot and I proposed such a strategy.</s>

<s sid="17" annotators="A B C D">The approach is simple: a redoubled effort to reduce infections and deaths rapidly in the malaria “heartland” (i.e., equatorial Africa and a handful of other areas around the world) should be accompanied by a campaign to roll back the disease from its current margins.</s>

<s sid="18" annotators="C">Malaria has natural limits, determined by latitude, altitude and, in some cases, human intervention.</s>

<s sid="19" annotators="A B C">The countries at the fringe of this zone typically benefit from a range of factors that make complete elimination of malaria possible, including lower transmission of the disease, stronger health systems, and relative national wealth.</s>

<s sid="20">Most importantly, these countries are not surrounded by malaria.</s>

<s sid="21" annotators="B C">As they successfully eliminate malaria, they will provide a new malaria-free anchor that will enable their neighbors, which have been pursuing aggressive control measures in the interim, to embark on their own eradication campaigns.</s>

<s sid="22">In this way, malaria will literally be rolled back from its current borders.</s>

<s sid="23">This strategy has begun to emerge organically, without prompting from the global community.</s>

<s sid="24">In the Pacific, Vanuatu and the Solomon Islands, at the far southeastern margin of the malaria endemic zone, have embarked on an eradication campaign with support from the Australian government.</s>

<s sid="25" annotators="C">Across the globe, the Southern Africa Development Community has set a goal of eliminating malaria from its four southernmost members – Botswana, Namibia, South Africa, and Swaziland – by 2015.</s>

<s sid="26">To do so, they are in active discussions with their northern neighbors, and innovative cross-border collaborations are being developed, building on the model of the highly successful partnership between Mozambique, South Africa, and Swaziland.</s>

<s sid="27">Other malaria margins where eradication efforts are underway are China, the Philippines, and Central America.</s>

<s sid="28" annotators="A C D">More than one million people die each year from malaria, most of them are children.</s>

<s sid="29">Yet malaria is a preventable and treatable disease.</s>

<s sid="30">The task of eliminating malaria, country by country, and eventually reaching global eradication, is underway.</s>

<s sid="31">This time, we must not rest until it is completed.</s>

</document>

</cluster>